<!--

Copyright 2018 Double Precision, Inc.
See COPYING for distribution information.

-->

<chapter id="connection_thread">
  <title>Connection threads and callbacks</title>

  <para>
    As mentioned briefly in the introduction, the &app; creates an internal
    execution thread for the connection with the display server.
    &app; takes care of starting and stopping the connection thread.
    The connection thread gets started when needed, and the connection
    thread gets stopped when the last top level window,
    or an explicitly constructed
    <link linkend="connections_and_screens">connection</link> object,
    goes out of scope and gets destroyed.
  </para>

  <para>
    The connection thread takes care of updating the display, and
    processing internal display protocol messages. The connection thread
    also executes application-specified lambdas or other callable
    objects in response to specific events.
  </para>

  <para>
    The connection thread resumes its normal duties after the application
    callback returns. Application callbacks should not get bogged down
    with long-running tasks, as this will result in the application
    window appearing to be frozen. Callbacks should be minimal, and consist
    of little more than sending a message of some kind, or setting a flag.
  </para>

  <section id="callback_signatures">
    <title>Callback calling conventions</title>

    <para>
      Typical example: a
      main window's <methodname>on_delete</methodname>() method
      sets the callback that gets executed in when the window's close
      button gets clicked:
    </para>

    <blockquote>
      <informalexample>
	<programlisting>
main_window->on_delete([close_flag]
    (ONLY IN_THREAD,
     const &ns;::w::busy &amp;ignore)
     {
         close_flag->close();
     });</programlisting>
      </informalexample>
    </blockquote>

    <para>
      This is an example of the calling convention &appshort; uses for
      invoking its callbacks by the internal execution thread.
      The callback's first parameter is a reference to an internal
      object that represents the connection thread itself.
      The callback's first parameter gets specified as
      <quote><literal>ONLY IN_THREAD</literal></quote>, this declares a
      parameter named <varname>IN_THREAD</varname> that carries this
      internal reference.
    </para>

    <para>
      This calling convention serves a dual purpose:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  This identifies lambdas that always get invoked by the library's'
	  internal connection
	  thread, as well as object methods that can only be invoked
	  from the connection thread.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A lambda that receives the <varname>IN_THREAD</varname> parameter
	  can call other functions and methods by forwarding to them this
	  parameter:
	</para>

	<blockquote>
	  <informalexample>
	    <programlisting>
lm-&gt;remove_item(IN_THREAD, 0);</programlisting>
	  </informalexample>
	</blockquote>

	<para>
	  The only way to receive the <varname>IN_THREAD</varname> parameter
	  is by having a function executed by the internal connection thread.
	  In this manner only <varname>IN_THREAD</varname> code can invoke
	  other <varname>IN_THREAD</varname> code.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      The <quote><literal>THREAD_CALLBACK</literal></quote> designation
      is just an alias. for the parameter's type:
      </para>

    <blockquote>
      <informalexample>
	<programlisting>
main_window->on_delete([close_flag]
    (THREAD_CALLBACK,
     const &ns;::w::busy &amp;ignore)
     {
         close_flag->close();
     });</programlisting>
      </informalexample>
    </blockquote>

    <para>
      <quote><literal>ONLY IN_THREAD</literal></quote> and
      <quote><literal>THREAD_CALLBACK</literal></quote> mean the same
      thing. The only difference is that the former declares a named
      parameter, called <quote>IN_THREAD</quote>; and the latter is just
      a parameter type declaration. This <methodname>on_delete</methodname>()
      example does not need to call any other connection thread code, so
      it doesn't need to forward its thread parameter anywhere.
      Using the <literal>THREAD_CALLBACK</literal> designation is a little
      but more descriptive.
    </para>

    <para>
      Some &appshort; objects provide overloaded versions of the same
      method, with and without the <literal>ONLY IN_THREAD</literal>
      designation. Except where noted, &appshort; makes all changes to
      display elements from the internal connection thread.
      Application code invoking the non-<literal>IN_THREAD</literal>
      method does not immediately update the display element. What happens
      is that a message gets sent to the connection thread, which processes
      it at the first available opportunity.
    </para>

    <para>
      But a callback that gets executed by the connection thread and receives
      the <varname>IN_THREAD</varname> parameter has the ability to
      use the <literal>ONLY IN_THREAD</literal> overload, which makes the
      change immediately. An
      <varname>IN_THREAD</varname> code is free to invoke the
      non-<varname>IN_THREAD</varname> overload also, but this will not
      result in any changes until the callback returns, and the connection
      thread resumes processing its internal messages.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="callback_invocation">
    <title>Callback invocations</title>

    <para>
      The &connection_thread; thread is completely asynchronous. This
      means that uninstalling or replacing an existing callback does not
      guarantee that the existing callback gets removed, and is no longer
      in effect, cannot be called again. It's possible that the connection
      thread is in the middle of running the existing callback. The
      replacement or the uninstallation takes effect only when the
      execution thread processes the internal message to uninstall the
      callback, or install a replacement callback.
    </para>

    <para>
      Callbacks get wrapped into a reference-counted object, which exists
      as long as the callback remains active.
      This means that the
      application's callbacks should safely capture anything they
      need by value (subject to <link linkend="callbackrefs">restrictions
	on creating circular references</link>).
      &libcxx;'s reference-counted objects (which are,
      incidentally, are used to build the &app; itself) are an excellent
      suggestion. The callback and the main application coordinate their
      mutual dependency through some reference-counted object, and the
      underlying framework handles the cleanup easily:
    </para>

    <blockquote>
      <informalexample>
	<programlisting>
main_window->on_delete([close_flag]
    (ONLY IN_THREAD,
     const &ns;::w::busy &amp;ignore)
     {
         close_flag->close();
     });</programlisting>
      </informalexample>
    </blockquote>

    <para>
      This examples captures the <varname>close_flag</varname> object, which
      is a
      <ulink url="&refobj;">reference-counted object</ulink>. A reference
      to the lambda itself gets stored internally, in the
      <varname>main_window</varname>, keeping the captured reference.
      The main application has another reference on the
      <varname>close_flag</varname> object, and responds by leaving
      <varname>main_window</varname>'s scope, which destroys this object,
      that represents the application's main window.
    </para>

    <para>
      This closes the window and destroys the object, together with its
      <varname>on_delete</varname> callback, and its captured object reference,
      and the application's second reference to the same object goes out of
      scope as well.
    </para>

    <para>
      It is immaterial which reference to the <varname>close_flag</varname>
      goes out of scope first and last. Whichever reference goes out of
      scope last, the <varname>close_flag</varname> object gets destroyed,
      deleting all the memory associated with it.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="connflush">
    <title>Flushing the display buffers</title>

    <para>
      Other toolkit libraries typically offer the means
      to <quote>flush</quote> their
      output buffer and send all buffered commands to the display
      server in order to update the application's window and have it reflect
      all buffered changes to its fields and display elements. There is no such
      direct equivalent with &appshort;. Its internal &connection_thread;
      automatically flushes the display buffer after the thread finishes
      all pending processes, and has nothing else to do.
    </para>

    <para>
      However, sometimes its necessary to do something analogous with
      &appshort;. One such case is creating a large window with many
      display elements, and a complicated layout, which may take a noticably
      long period of time, and cannot be avoided. Using
      <link linkend="busy"><methodname>get_wait_busy_mcguffin</methodname></link>()
      changes the current pointer to a <quote>busy</quote> icon, but
      this icon doesn't appear until the display message that creates it gest
      flushed to the display server; and if the connection thread is busy,
      creating this large window, this won't happen until that's already done.
    </para>

    <para>
      Here's one possible solution:
    </para>

    <blockquote>
      <informalexample>
	<programlisting>
button-&gt;on_activate(
   [button=&ns;::make_weak_capture(button)]
   (ONLY IN_THREAD,
    const &ns;::w::callback_trigger_t &amp;trigger,
    const x::w::busy &amp;mcguffin_factory)
   {
       auto got=button.get();
       if (!got)
           return;
       auto &amp; [button]=*got;

       &ns;::ref&lt;&ns;::obj&gt; mcguffin=mcguffin_factory.get_wait_busy_mcguffin();
       button-&gt;in_thread_idle(
          [mcguffin]
          (ONLY IN_THREAD)
          {
               // Now create the large window
          });
   });</programlisting>
      </informalexample>
    </blockquote>

    <para>
      <varname>button</varname> is some button. Its
      <link linkend="activation"><methodname>on_activate</methodname></link>()
      &callback; weakly-captures itself, in order to
      <link linkend="callbackrefs">prevent a circular reference</link>.
      After dispensing with the formalities of dealing with the weak reference,
      <methodname>get_wait_busy_mcguffin()</methodname> acquires the
      <link linkend="busy"><quote>busy mcguffin</quote></link>, to block
      input processing and change the pointer to the <quote>busy</quote>
      icon, before scheduling an <methodname>in_thread_idle</methodname>()
      callback.
    </para>

    <para>
      Invoking a display element's
      <methodname>in_thread_idle</methodname>() method schedules the
      specified callback to get executed by the &connection_thread; after
      the connection thread finishes all of its pending work and flushes
      the display buffer. The pending work here consists of changing the
      pointer icon, and everything else that happened previously.
    </para>

    <para>
      Once that's done, the second callback executes, and takes its time
      to do whatever it needs to do. The second callback intentionally
      captures the reference to the busy mcguffin, so all input processing
      stops and the pointer icon continues to indicate <quote>busy</quote>
      until the callback executes and finishes.
    </para>

    <para>
      This can be used to mimic the classical <quote>flush</quote> function:
    </para>

    <blockquote>
      <informalexample>
	<programlisting>
class flagObj : virtual public &ns;::obj {

public:

    typedef &ns;::mpcobj&lt;bool&gt; value_t;

    value_t value=false;

    void signal()
    {
        value_t::lock lock{value};

        *lock=true;
        lock.notify_all();
    }

    void wait()
    {
        value_t::lock lock{value};

        lock.wait([&amp;] { return *lock; });
    }
};

void flush(const &ns;::w::element &amp;e)
{
    auto flag=&ns;::ref&lt;flagObj&gt;::create();

    e->in_thread_idle([flag]
              (THREAD_CALLBACK)
              {
                  flag->signal();
              });

    flag->wait();
}</programlisting>
      </informalexample>
    </blockquote>

    <para>
      This works only if <methodname>flush</methodname>() is not called
      from the connection thread itself. <methodname>flush</methodname>()
      uses <methodname>in_thread_idle</methodname>() to schedule execution
      of a callback
      that sets a flag and signals a condition variable, then waits for
      the condition variable to get signalled. If
      <methodname>flush</methodname>() itself gets called
      from the connection thread, this will wait forever for itself to set
      the flag and signal the condition variable.
    </para>

    <para>
      There's also <methodname>in_thread</methodname>() in addition to
      <methodname>in_thread_idle</methodname>().
      <methodname>in_thread</methodname>() does not wait for the connection
      thread to be idle, but executes the callback after all higher-priority
      processing is complete, but before doing any low priority work like
      drawing the actual display elements.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->
