<!--

Copyright 2014-2018 Double Precision, Inc.
See COPYING for distribution information.

-->

<preface id="index">
  <title>&app;</title>
  <section id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <?dbhtml-include href="demoreel.inc.html"?>

    <para>
      &appshort; is an optional add-on library to &libcxx;
      that implements a basic X user interface toolkit with a modern
      C++17 <acronym>API</acronym> and without any dependencies on large
      Gnome (GTK) or QT libraries. The only dependencies are
      toolkit-independent
      libraries that are not tied to any particular desktop environment.
      See <xref linkend="INSTALL" /> for more information.
      &appshort; aims to make it possible to quickly implement a simple,
      basic, no-frills X user interface in C++.
      Notable features:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Implements classical, tradition UI elements &mdash;
	  labels, text input fields,
	  lists, combo-boxes, menus, and dialogs &mdash; updated to modern
	  UI standards: confirming the last character typed into a
	  password field before masking it, predictive selection of
	  combo-box entries, spin buttons for numerical input fields, etc...
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Clean
	  modern look, with mild gradient shading for a subtle, non-intrusive
	  3D effect.
	  Fully keyboard-accessible. All display elements have full
	  keyboard navigation, where possible. No explicit application
	  support is needed. Even scroll-bars have keyboard controls.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Takes full advantage of modern C++17 language features. Lambdas
	  handle UI events (button clicks, menu selections, and other
	  activity). Variant types provide compact means for
	  selecting alternative options.
	  All display elements are reference-counted objects.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Fully scalable and themeable UI uses a
	  <link linkend="sxg">library-specific
	    scalable graphic format</link>, to easily scale all UI elements
	  to a user-preferred size.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  &app; does not force the application to use an event-driven
	  design. &app; runs in an internal execution thread that handles all
	  X events. The library's execution thread
	  continues to update the display elements, and process X events
	  as needed, all by itself, while the main application performs a
	  long-running task (with all pointer and button activity suspended).
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  &app; is a compositing toolkit. The underlying video hardware
	  must implement the X RENDER extension. This should be supported by all
	  modern video hardware.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Anti-aliased fonts get rendered by the Freetype library.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      &app; is free software, distributed under the terms of the
      <link linkend="COPYING">GPL, version 3</link>.
    </para>

    <section id="status">
      <title>Status</title>

      <para>
	&app; is in active development. The most recent build implements
	the <link linkend="itemlayoutmanager">item layout manager</link>.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  &install;

</preface>

<!--
Local Variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "book" "preface")
End:
-->
